About

I use scientific computing to study the structure and properties of atomic nuclei. I have worked on a number of different topics in nuclear structure and reaction theory, quantum chemistry, quantum information theory, and machine learning. All of my work involves the application of high performance computing (HPC) to quantum many-body physics.

My (ongoing) Ph.D. project is on the integrated shell model and Hauser-Feshbach description of beta-delayed neutron emission.

Last updated October, 2022.

University Education

- PhD Computational Science, expected 2023 Joint Doctoral Program with UC Irvine and San Diego State University
- MS Physics, 2018 San Diego State University
- BA Physics, 2016 University of California, Berkeley

Training

- FRIB-TA Summer School: A practical walk through formal scattering theory, 2021
 - Course resources
 - Connecting bound states, resonances, and scattering states in exotic nuclei and beyond
- Agile Development Practices and Tools: A Guided Tour, 2020
 - Sustainable Horizons Institute introduction to agile software development
 - Collaborative source control using git, GitHub, and git workflows
- Technical Writing Workshop, 2019
 - LLNL PLS Directorate sponsored two-part writing class
 - Session 1: Structuring your research paper
 - Session 2: Clear, accurate, concise writing

Research Positions

- $\bullet\,$ PhD Candidate LLNL, 2022 to present
 - New predictive capability for reaction and decay properties of fission fragments
- - Developed software and theory to describe atomic nuclei using the nuclear shell model and computational science

- Glenn T. Seaborg Institute (GTSI) Summer Intern Seaborg Institute, LLNL, Summer 2021
- High Energy Density Physics Intern Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory, Summer 2018, 2019, and 2020
 - Developed Python code to do MCMC parameter estimation for statistical nuclear reaction codes in order to combine surrogate data and theory
 - Employed code for sensitivity studies assessing approximations in the surrogate reactions method
 - Modified and ran four Hauser-Feshbach model codes
- Graduate Student UC Irvine, Department of Chemistry with Filipp Furche, Fall 2019 and Spring 2020.
 - Collaborated to develop formalism for Nuclear-Electronic Orbital method using time-dependent density functional theory

Professional

- Served as a referee for Physical Review C
- Experience writing proposals for DOE, NNSA, and other funding sources
- Graduate Teaching Associate San Diego State University, Department of Physics, during 2016 - 2020.
 - Independently lead lectures and exams for introductory-level physics lab courses
 - Modernized the manual for Physics 182A/195L Laboratory for online deployment in Spring 2020

Awards

- LLNL WCI Academic Collaboration Team University Program (ACT-UP) Award
- Graduate S-STEM Scholarship, 2018-2020

Code

- Major projects: Modern Fortran, Python, Bash
- Minor tasks: C++, openMP, MPI, Mathematica, MATLAB, R

Projects

- Wigner A library of functions for computation of Wigner 3-j, 6-j and 9-j symbols, written in modern Fortran.
 - Repository
 - Docs

- DMFortFactor A fast Fortran code for WIMP-nucleus form factors and differential event rate spectra. Written in modern Fortran with an optional Python interface. Parallel execution with OpenMP.
 - Repository
 - Docs
- PANASH Proton and neutron approximate shell model code. Not yet released.
- COMMCAS Computational Model Monte Carlo Sampler. Not yet released.

Research

Papers

- "Proton-neutron entanglement in the nuclear shell model" by C. Johnson and O. Gorton To be submitted to J. Phys. G. Pre-print: arXiv:2210.14338
- "dmscatter: A Fast Program for WIMP-Nucleus Scattering" by O. Gorton,
 C. Johnson, C. Jiao, J. Nikoleyczik Submitted to Comp. Phys. Comms.
 Pre-print: arXiv:2209.09187
- "Cross sections for neutron-induced reactions from surrogate data: revisiting the Weisskopf-Ewing approximation for (n,n') and (n,2n) reactions" by O. Gorton and J. E. Escher Submitted to Phys. Rev. C., pending review. Pre-print: arXiv:2102.03452
- "Measurements of proton capture in the A=100-110 mass region: Constraints of the 111In(gamma,p)/(gamma,n) branching point relevant to the gamma-process" by O. Olivas-Gomez, A. Simon, O. Gorton, J. E. Escher et al. Published November 2020 Phys. Rev. C, 102, 055806

Proceedings

- "A Problem in the Statistical Description of Beta-Delayed Neutron Emission" by O. Gorton, C. Johnson, and J. Escher to be submitted to proceedings of 15th International Conference on Nuclear Data for Science and Technology (ND2022). Preprint: arXiv:2210.05904
- "Neutron capture cross sections from surrogate reaction data and theory: connecting the pieces with a Markov-Chain Monte Carlo approach" by O. Gorton and J. E. Escher – Published September 2020 Spring Proceedings in Physics. Preprint: arXiv:1905:03055

Thesis

 "Efficient Modeling of Nuclei Through Coupling of Proton and Neutron Wavefunctions" by O. Gorton, Advisor: C. Johnson – Masters Thesis (2018) San Diego State University, 2018

Presentations

- "Nuclear Shell Model to the Rescue: Efforts to Resolve a Mystery in Beta Delayed Neutron Emission" by O. Gorton, C. Johnson, J. Escher – talk given at APS Division of Nuclear Physics Fall 2022 Meeting (New Orleans, October 2022).
- "Crisis in Beta-Delayed Neutron Emission: Shell Model to the Rescue" by O. Gorton, C. Johnson, J. Escher talk given at Nuclear Data Conference (July 2022).
- "Proton and Neutron Approximate Shell Model: Factorization-based Importance Truncation" by O. Gorton, C. Johnson, J. Escher poster given at Nuclear Structure Conference (June 2022).
- "DMFortFactor: A Fast and Accessible for Computing WIMP-Nucleus-Scattering Event-Rates" by O. Gorton, C. Johnson, C. Jiao talk given at DNP21 APS Conference (October 2021).
- "Better MCMC for Nuclear Data using emcee and B-DJINN" by O. C. Gorton, J. E. Escher, K. O. Bergstrom, M. K. Kruse talk given at LLNL Summer Slam 2021.
- "Nuclear Physics for WIMPs" by O. Gorton and C. W. Johnson talk given at SDSU SIAM Student Chapter Summer Colloquium Series, Friday July 2, 2021.
- "Cross subsections for neutron reactions from surrogate measurements: Revisiting the Weisskopf-Ewing approximation" by O. Gorton and J. E. Escher DNP20 APS Conference (October 2020).
- "Can we get rid of the theorists?" by O. Gorton and J. E. Escher LLNL Summer Slam talk (August 2020).
- "Big Picture and Background for Nuclear-Electronic Orbital (NEO) Approach: Calculating Mixed Nucleon-Electron Wave Functions" by O. Gorton progress talk presented for the Furche Group, Chemistry Department, UC Irvine (March 2020).
- "Indirect measurements of nuclear cross subsections: tempering experimental results with theory" by O. Gorton and J. E. Escher HEDP Exit Talk (September 2019).
- "Sensitivity Study of the Surrogate Method" by O. Gorton and J. E. Escher
 poster presented at LLNL Student Poster Symposium (August 2019).
- "Temperature and Entropy in the Nuclear Shell Model" by O. Gorton and C. W. Johnson poster presented at SDSU ACCESS event (April 2019).
- "Proton Neutron Interacting Shell Model: Order of Magnitude Reduction for Medium Mass Nuclei" by O. Gorton and C. Johnson poster presentated at SDSU annual research symposium (March 2019).

- "Neutron capture cross subsections from surrogate reaction data and theory: connecting the pieces with a Markov-Chain Monte Carlo approach" by O. Gorton and J. E. Escher poster presented at CNR18, September 2018.
- "A Markov Chain Monte Carlo Tool for Hauser-Feshbach Codes" by O. Gorton and J.E. Escher HEDP Exit Talk (August 2018).

Climbing

In my free time I enjoy rock climbing.

Top